good evening living Mana family how's
everyone doing I hope that you guys have
been blessed it's been a while it's been
a minute since we've been able to talk
been able to study together to be able
to uh spend some time with each other
but um I can be honest with you 2025 has
been has started off a little rough for
me um as as I've been able to uh finish
a lot of the goals for 202 for entering
to 2025 has been an adjustment we've
been having some crazy weather here in
Alabama and then I got sick and then the
list goes on and as we know life be
lifing but um I'm just so grateful for
the opportunity to be with you guys once
again my name is Lami Richardson I am
the youth young adult uh uh Pastor for
the living manner church and on Thursday
nights this program is directly for our
young adults and our youth um these
messages are going to be tailored to the
things that we struggle with now this is
going to be a blessing for anyone but we
wanted to create this safe place for
these young for our young adult
community to come in to ask questions to
really engage in the conversations that
we are having whether it be on testimony
Thursdays or through our various topics
that we'll be unpacking uh on Thursday
nights through our time together tonight
is going to be a very great topic a
topic that I don't believe we talk about
enough and if I'm being honest this is
something that was introduced to me a
few months ago as I went to a uh a
three-day Life app conference and it was
a conference that really changed my life
and in one of those sessions they talked
about addiction and as I kind of dug
into a little bit more and understanding
about addiction I realized that there is
a lot of things that we as a church as a
members as bodies as members of the
church and as the body of Christ we
struggle with addictions and we
sometimes minimize addictions to being
gravitating to drinking or or or drugs
or whatever it may be but actually there
are things that we do under the guise of
God that could be an addiction and
allowing us to uh escape from the
realities of life and so we're going to
talk about the topic of addiction but
we're also going to talk about how we
can find healing and wholeness in Christ
so I just want to welcome everybody once
again to tonight's topic and study uh
good evening Clint good to see you um
the blessed in family blessings to
everyone
uh so glad for you guys to be and uh
here with us tonight so we're going to
Dive Right In into our topic tonight and
if you have any questions please place
them in the in the chat and we'll try to
address them at the end of this
presentation if not please please please
join um join our app in our community um
at Mighty networks and join the safe
place uh and is that is there where we
have our community and we're able to
engage and talk about what we have uh
learned on our during our time together
on Thursday nights but let's bow our
heads for a word of prayer invite the
Holy Spirit to be with us and we're
going to Dive Right In to tonight's
topic let us pray father just want to
thank you again for your love for your
grace and for your mercy I ask that Lami
Richard man i' be heard or seing but
that your son Jesus Christ may be
uplifted and that every single person
who is tuning now or tuning later may be
drawn to that beautiful image that is
our our Lord and our Savior Jesus Christ
we love you we thank you for we ask this
in Jesus precious and holy name amen
and amen so if we can get the slides
onto the screen tonight's topic is
entitled addiction healing and wholeness
now there is going to be a video that
we're going to be showing but I want to
kind of introduce what is addiction what
is addiction addiction isn't just about
drugs it isn't about alcohol or
pornography it can also disguise itself
as overworking overly invested in family
or children or even immersing yourself
in your faith as an escape from dealing
with your reality so notice that
addiction isn't just limited to drugs
alcohol and pornography it can be the
very things that we do in our everyday
lives that is causing us to focus all of
our time and energy on this thing
because we are ultimately wanting to
escape something and we're going to talk
about that here as we continue our time
together so when we we are addicted to
video games when we are addicted to
overworking we are addicted to our our
passions right the the real question you
want to ask yourself is what are you
trying to avoid or to escape I I can't
tell you how often we spend our time
scroll asly ending on Tik Tok or binge
watching our favorite show on Netflix or
whatever it may be to try to escape the
reality that we're living in and Saints
if if if I'm being honest with you 2025
has been crazy we're only a month and a
half into this year and it already I
just need to take a break from life I
need to take a break from people I need
to take a break from television I need
to take a break from social media
because I realize something about myself
and I don't know if you notice this
about yourself as well I'm only
human there's only amount of things that
I can take on for myself because I have
my own stresses in life and when life
gets too stressful and overwhelming I
notice that I immerse myself in the
things that I enjoy not because I find
uh enjoyment but because in reality I'm
trying to avoid dealing with something
or escape the reality that I'm in and so
that is the question that we want to ask
ourselves why is it that I gravitate to
this thing and invest so much time and
energy what am I trying to avoid what am
I trying to escape there is a video and
if it can't be played I'm sure it
probably won't be able to play but there
is a video and I'll share this link in
our Mighty net n Works um group so that
way you guys can watch this video
unfortunately the video uh was not being
able to download on the file but
nonetheless I do have the summary of
what this video is describing so this
video is from uh Gabor matate he's a
Hondurian born Canadian physician and he
actually talks about the background uh
he has a background in family practice
and is more focused on childhood
development and Trauma and so he
explains how the potential lifelong
impacts of physical and mental health U
not only creates uh uh disease cancer
ADH but also it can uh trigger
addictions that you and I possess so I
want you to notice a summary of what um
Dr uh matate describes what addiction is
so addiction is stems from a childhood
trauma that disrupts the fun fundamental
needs of attachment and authenticity
leading individuals to seek relief in
addictive behaviors so all of these
addictive behaviors that we possess
stems from from sort of traumatic event
that we had as children and it's in
reality we are trying to seek
authenticity and so we find our true
selves in relief in and through
addictive behaviors but he also
describes in this video that trauma is
not just what happens to a person person
but it also affects our internal
disconnection from emotions and the body
resulting in negative perception
perspectives so I don't know if you ever
been through this but I know for me and
I and and I remember going through my
dark period in time a few years ago and
I was been watching a TV show on Amazon
I would refrain from naming the show
because you have no business watching it
just like I had no business watching it
during the time but I remember I was
depressed I remember that I could not uh
really grasp the things that was
happening to me during that time I got
laid off my savings was dwindling right
I was going through a a a a a heartbreak
I was going through a lot and the only
way that I can find relief was through
escaping through watching this TV show
and I remember watching this TV show for
two straight Seasons it had two seasons
no I think I had three seasons and each
episode was anywhere from 45 minutes to
an hour long and I never forget that
after sitting there on the couch for
over seven hours getting up from the
couch and going outside I remember that
just my my perspective of life change I
felt even more depressed I didn't look
at people the same I looked at everyone
with disgust I thought that everybody
was bad people and so it's it's
interesting that just me watching a TV
show and bend watching and and trying to
escape the realities of my own hurt my
own pain and trying to escape from it
instead of going to Christ right I was
pouring in my uh uh trying to pour in
myself into this TV show so much so that
I disconnected myself from my emotions I
no longer felt uh the pain that I was
experiencing because I was numbing it
through this TV show that I was watching
and so as a result I felt like all right
I don't like people I don't want to talk
to people I want to be isolated I want
to be alone all of those things caused
me to have negative perspectives of my
own reality and about people also he
States another point in this
video that not only is a childhood
trauma but also addiction is an attempt
listen to this to solve the problem of
disconnection caused by childhood trauma
and it provides temporary relief while
creating more problems in the long
run you see when we constantly avoid the
problem that is at hand
and we prolong the inevitable it ends up
being much more impactful and hurtful to
us the longer that we prolong dealing
with the issue that is at hand also we
see that recovery according to Doc uh to
to um to Dr uh matate he says that
recovery from addiction and Trauma
involves reconnecting with oneself and
finding the lost connection with the
body and emotions to regain in a sense
of self now I want to stop here and I
want to emphasize this point the only
way that we can truly have a meaningful
and impactful relationship with God is
if we know who we really
are and most of us have a version of
ourselves that is not true to who we
really are meaning that when we go to
church and we say uh the cliche sayings
happy Sabbath hallelujah amen right we
put on our our Sabbath best our Sunday
Best we go to church and and we present
the best version of our elves we know
that for that hour or two people are
never going to really see the inside of
what we are dealing with and so the only
way that we can truly recover the only
way that we can truly be in Christ or be
free in Christ is to regain the sense of
ourselves I I hope that's not being Lost
in Translation I I got a couple amens in
in the chat so I'm glad that you guys
are following with me so when I'm
scrolling count hours on on on social
media when I'm binge watching my
television when I'm immersing myself in
drugs and pornography or drinking or
whatever Vice it is that you're choosing
you're ultimately escaping dealing
something that is causing you to be
addicted because of a pain that you may
have experienced in the past that's
causing you to escape that reality
currently we have to come to the point
saints that we are reconnecting our
emotions our thoughts and our feelings
and aligning ourselves with our true
selves and giving that true version to
God right it's easy to go to God and say
God help me stop drinking cool I can
help you stop drinking but why are you
drinking in the first place are you
following what I'm saying like God is
trying to get to the why of the problem
he's trying to not just get to uh
ascertain the cause he is trying to get
to the root of the problem that you and
I are asking God to Deliver Us from so
we can't escape ourselves and and God is
calling us to reenter ourselves to know
who we really are our triggers our
thoughts our emotions and allowing us to
present our full version to God all
right so we're going to
continue I got a couple of minutes you
guys are with me praise the Lord so
summary the real purpose of addiction
and mental health treatment is
reconnecting it is reconnecting with
yourself and ultimately reconnecting
with your savior it is not to
disassociate yourself from reality but
saying okay there's pain there's hurt
there's there's there's sadness there's
anxiety there's depression there's these
over complicated emotions and I don't
need to escape from it I need to ask
myself why am I dealing with this am I
being honest with the experience that
I'm going through right so the real
purpose of addiction the real purpose of
mental health treatment is to reconnect
with yourself once again to not dis
associate yourself from yourself but
allowing individuals to recover and find
themselves once again and Saints I'm
going to tell you something through my
experience through my mental health
journey through my battles of anxiety
through my battles of depression through
my difficult moments in life God was
giving me the opportunity to reconnect
with myself and really see who I am at
my core are you following what I'm
saying he he wanted me to reconnect and
really see who is loami when it's all
said and done when everything is
Stripped Away who are you at your core
and so now as I go to God I'm saying God
this is who I am I realize that I have
these vices I realize that I have these
struggles I realize that I have these
these uh addictions in my life but I
know that these are just a symptom to a
deeper rooted cause and God can only
reveal to you what you're honest
about God can only reveal to you what
you are honest about
and many of us within the church are not
honest with ourselves so if we're not
honest with ourselves how is it that we
can be honest with God and if we're not
honest with God then how is it that we
can Minister and connect with people
around us when we are disassociated from
reality are you following what I'm
saying I love that Clint we do tend to
go through life blind to who we actually
are so so this is why we don't make
meaningful connections this is the
reason why we don't have much impact
when we try to evangelize and try to
witness to people people because your
reality is so so outside of people's
reality that you're no earthly good
right well just give it to God In Prayer
what does that even mean how do I do
that I did do that and I don't see God
answering my prayers well you just got
to have faith then what is Faith because
I thought I had Faith but I don't see
that my faith is exercising the belief
that I want to accomplish and Achieve
through my prayers to Christ we use all
these cliche answers but Saints God
allows us to go through these
experiences listen to me so that way we
can discover the key on how we had
victories in those dark
moments yeah I I stay silent for a
reason God does not want us to escape
reality he wants to embrace reality to
embrace who you are and the situations
and the circumstance and the feelings
that you are going through let us
continue let us continue so addiction is
a response to pain
I've have friends who do parlays who
gamble who who drink who smoke I I have
friends who do all of the the the the
ratchet things right that that culture
and Society said are and I realize that
at the end of the day those addictions
are simply a response to pain pain to
what addiction is not a moral failure or
weakness you're not your struggle you're
not your addiction I'm going to say that
again you are not your struggle you are
not your addiction those things do not
define who you are it is a a cry for us
to understand ourselves more deeply and
to see okay why am I responding to why
am I gravitating to this and what am I
trying to escape from so I just want to
emphasize that any addictions that you
may be having and I have my own
addictions I have my own vices that I
need to surrender to God and him and I
are working through it but I realize
that as much as I tell God God take this
thing away he says if I take it away and
something else happens in your life
you're just going to gravitate to the
very thing because you're not
understanding why you are gravitating to
it in the first place there is a pain
that is there but again you are not your
you're not morally a failure you're not
weak you're not any of this you are the
child of God you have been created in
His image and he's wanting to restore us
back into his image of redemption of
love and race at the end of the day
addiction is a survival mechanism to
soothe unhealed emotional
wounds is escaping from ourselves in the
reality of the pain that we've
experienced in the past or currently
experiencing it could be a divorce it
could be laying being laid off at a job
it could be parents your children don't
want to do anything with God and they
don't want to do anything with you those
are all real pain and sometimes in our
addic in in our in in our pain we
respond thinking we're doing God's work
in a reality we're trying to escape the
pain of that reality that just sat in so
what is the root cause the root cause to
all addiction is simply this it is
trauma or unmet needs or unresolved pain
those are the three major things so I
want you to understand that any
addiction any vices that you are
constantly gravitating to when you
experience pain it's either stemming
from some sort of traumatic event that
you have not resolved or unmet needs or
unresolved pain now you understand okay
when I experience pain when I experience
a trauma response right when I spiral
when I curse people out when I get
irritated all of those things is a
response to something that has bothered
you that you have not resolved or
surrendered to God or have dealt with it
yourself right or process to understand
what it is that's causing this response
those are the three things trauma un
needs as well as unresolved pain and
Saints I can't tell you how
many faithful saints of God have gone
through the entire life masking their
pain through religion masking through
pain through their faith because there
was some trauma unresolved pain from
things that happened to them in the past
whether it be from mother father Uncle
church member you name it but I realize
especially with the young people young
adults a lot of our addiction is a
response to unmet needs and a lot of
those unmet needs come from lack of
community lack of purpose lack of Drive
lack of understanding what you've been
created to do and what you've been able
and the skills and the tools that God
has given you to make an impact in the
world and I realize that a lot of young
people young adults people my age
gravitate to addiction because there is
an unmet need that is there there's an
emotional void that they're not getting
so they gravitate to these addictions so
I hope that you guys are gravitating to
these tools or or these principles
because when a young person comes to you
and says listen I'm addicted to
pornography I'm addicted to drinking I'm
addicted to binge watching you can now
immediately say and understand that this
person is not their addiction this is a
wound they're responding to a wound
let's go back right addiction is not
sorry let me I skip forward addiction is
not a moral failure or a weakness
they're not weak the Bible tells us that
when we are weak that's when we are
strong so the fact that we actually
admit that we have an addiction is
evidence that we're about to gain
Victory and strength in this area that
is weak are you following what I'm
saying so now that we understand what
addiction is before we go to Matthew
11:28 the three things and I if you need
to put it in the chat or write it down
because this is going to be so vital as
we minister to other people that as we
seek help as we seek healing as we seek
uh wholeness in Christ addiction is
simply a response to pain trauma or
unmet needs so young people what are the
unmet needs that you are experiencing
currently that's causing you to
gravitate to pornography causing you to
want to date anybody that you see Escape
in relationship escaping work escaping
you fill in the blank what is a trauma
or what is the unresolved pain but more
importantly what is the need that is
being unmet in your life and how can God
fill in that unmet need Matthew 11:28
tells us come to me all who are what
weary and burdened and what is the
promise that God gives to us and I will
give you rest many of us are dealing
with anxiety and depression and we've
lived with it so long that it now has
become a part of our character trait
I just had I just went to go to the
doctor uh earlier this week and and I
have white cold syndrome I'm not even G
to lie right but I I've reached that age
now that I got to make sure that I'm
doing my yearly check-ins I'm making
sure that I'm exercising drinking my
water taking my supplements doing all
the things that I can do but I realized
that the doctor was checking my blood
pressure and I'm sitting here like their
blood pressure is a little high for
somebody so young and I'm like okay well
the seven laws of Health am I getting a
lot of sun maybe not because the it's
been a crazy winter have I've been
exercising yes not as consistent I'm I'm
doing the checklist right and about two
days ago three days ago I was sitting on
my couch and I was about to eat dinner
and I took a deep breath and I reentered
myself and I felt my heart going 100
miles a minute I'm like God why am I
it's it's 7 o'clock I'm winding down
like the day is over what's causing this
stress or this anxiety and I realized
there was a lot of thoughts that I was
placing in my mind the last two weeks
about finances about the next step what
is the next Direction I'm carrying other
burdens that are not that wasn't
pertaining to me I'm borrowing the
stress and applying it to me and
applying it into my life and I'm
realizing that's what's causing this
high blood pressure this is why the
doctor's like well you you seem to be
doing everything okay and it was my
anxiety and I realized okay God anxiety
is an indicator that something um that
I'm trying to control something that I
have no control over I'm not trying to
control and I walked through God with
that with through that conversation he
revealed to me the things that I was
trying to control that I had no business
controlling he says you don't worry
about tomorrow tomorrow is not promised
why are you stress about yesterday
that's already been passed worry about
today and so this is why Matthew 11:28
is a call God says come to me with your
addictions come to me with all your
unmet needs come to me with your trauma
come to me with your unresolved pain and
I will will give you
rest but the only way that you come to
him Saints is first you understand that
there is something for you to go to him
for
for am I being honest about my unmet
needs am I being honest about my pain am
I being honest about my trauma it's so
easy to talk about the addiction but are
we understanding what's causing that
addiction all right that's a promise but
here are the three things I want to
share here are the hitting addictions
that we find ourselves doing in the
church and as Believers that we don't
think our addictions but in reality fit
under those three main uh criterias as
to why we are addicted pain un unmet
needs or trauma check this out how many
of y'all
overwork and I'm not talking about
working 50 hours a week at your job I'm
talking about you cannot sit down and
relax you're always constantly having to
do something and if you do sit down to t
a take a break immediately you feel
guilty about taking a break and taking
the
rest could it be that you're trying to
Earth trying to earn your worth through
prod productivity could it be that the
reason why you cannot relax and chill
and just enjoy the fruits of your labor
the reason why you're overworking could
it be that you're finding your worth
through being
productive I can tell you that I was a
over worker and the reason why I was a
over worker because I grew up in a home
where the constant saying was if you
don't work you don't eat and it didn't
matter if I went to school you know what
I'm saying six days five days out the
week if I was sleeping past 8 o'clock
you're lazy you need to get up and you
need to do something so as a teenager
and an adolescent as a young young ad as
a young person I'm walking around doing
random things because I can't be seen
not doing anything because if I am not
doing anything then I'm gonna be labeled
all of these things and then scripture
is being used to try to uh uh justify
you know I'm saying the reason why I'm
doing all of these other
things so Clint you said you don't know
how to relax you got to ask yourself why
what is causing right again trauma pain
or unmet needs so we overwork and the
reason why we overwork listen to this is
because we're trying to earn our worth
through productivity so who told you
that the only value you bring is by
producing and constantly working who
told you that where did idea come from
that's a question how about
overparenting I get this a lot I get a
lot of conversations from parents asking
me to talk to their children oh they
heard my testimony you're such a beacon
of light and if only my son I'm like
wait a minute wait a minute wait a
minute wait a minute why are you
constantly putting all these rules and
restrictions on your on your child what
is it that you're trying to oh maybe
you're trying to find identity solely in
in the family role that you play Maybe
subconsciously you don't think you're a
good mother or you're a good father so
you have to overpar to show that if my
kid is straight that I can show to the
world how good of a parent I am because
I grew up listening to the lies of my
parents saying that I'm never a good kid
could it
be another hidden addition is is faith
escapism we use spirituality to avoid
facing personal struggle how are you
doing today well you know God is good
all the time all the time God is good
you know all right what does that even
mean you know we just got to keep on
living we we we we we immerse ourselves
at church we immerse our immerse
ourselves through religious things
through Bible studies we we immerse
oursel in the church but we never
address the really thing that we're
personally struggling
with we we don't go in to to our our
small groups and let them be and be
honest with them and let them know
listen man I'm I'm really struggling I'm
struggling to pay rent I'm struggling
with my worth I I I'm I went through
this devastating uh breakup and and lost
my job whatever it may be right but
instead of dealing with the reality and
facing the personal struggles you're
going through oh I'm just going to
immerse myself in living Mana seven days
out the week I'm gonna be in every group
I'm GNA be in every Bible
study what are you trying to escape from
what am I hiding
from those are the hidden addictions
that sometimes we Overlook because it's
good it's good that I'm being productive
it's good that I care about my family
and my children and their salvation it's
good that I'm participating in the
church and all these activities enjoying
small groups and bible studies etc etc
listening to constant sermons all the
time I don't listen to nothing secular
all sermons all hymns all the time
praise God but at the end of the day are
you dealing with the reality of your own
life are you trying to avoid facing your
personal struggles and using
spirituality to escape from your current
reality
is it that you're really wanting to be a
good parent or are you really fearful of
your kid being lost because you don't
have an assurance of Salvation you
yourself do you find your value in doing
all of these random things because at
the end of the day if I do not work then
people are going to call me lazy and I
cannot believe that lie or that truth
about myself so I'm going to prove
everyone that I'm not lazy so I'm just
going to constantly work and work myself
to
death
h we'll continue what am I hiding from
that is a question so the role of Shame
and Trauma listen to this addiction
often stems from shame I'm not enough or
I'm not unworthy now my question is if
these are the thoughts that you're
coming into your mind my question is is
what does God say about you God says I
am enough God says I am worthy but if
the constant thoughts and the lies that
I keep telling myself or allow Humanity
to tell myself or social media or
culture or the world to tell me the
addiction stems from saying there's
shame
there because in reality I'm not good
enough this is why yo as Kendrick Lamar
said cut the TV off just cut it off cut
off social media because once we start
doing is start comparing ourselves to
the things that we watch well look they
have a happy family oh look she has a
great body oh look she she she's uh
successful financially and look at my
reality there's shame there now because
now you're comparing yourself to other
people that you have no relationship
with and the truth of the matter is
social media only gives you the 15
seconds of the best version of their
lives they don't tell you what's
happening the other 23 hours of the day
right but the role of Shame and Trauma
plays a a part of the addiction there is
stems some sort of Shame and that shame
stems from I'm not enough and I'm not
worthy so ultimately trauma reshapes our
brain leaving us notice this vulnerable
to seek relief in unhealthy ways so
because I'm not enough because I am not
worthy is why I'm just going to lay my
I'm just going to sleep with whoever
shows any interest in me anyone who says
I think I'm cute I'm gonna try to date
why because at the end of the day I'm
not enough or I'm not worthy and the
reason why I feel that way is because my
mom and my dad growing up told me that I
wasn't worthy and I was never good
enough that I was fat that I need to
lose weight all of those things play a
part into Who We Are are and why we uh
gravitate to the things that we
gravitate
to but here's the key Reflections how do
we heal from the root and not just the
symptom and I see a lot of prayers from
Saints including my prayers my prayers
will say Lord take this thing away if I
if you take this away if you take this
Vice if you take this addiction if you
take this struggle then I'll be a
perfect
Christian or God is saying maybe you
should look a little deeper and that's
what we're going to address as we wrap
up here in the next few
moments here's a Christian path to
Healing all right number one you have to
acknowledge the pain you have to be
honest with yourself and with God Psalms
34:18 tells us the Lord is close to the
who
brokenhearted but if you're not
acknowledging that you're broken then
how can God heal how can God draw close
how can God heal the pain that you're
not
acknowledging
right we have to acknowledge the pain we
have to be honest in the reality that
we're in and bring that to God so that
way he can draw close to us and start
that healing Journey that we all desire
to have an experience number two here is
so vital and so key we need to seek
support the Book of James tells us that
there's safety in community Godly
Community not just any Community people
that you can trust people that know you
better than you know yourself sometimes
right healing happens in community and
Saints I want to emphasize this is the
reason why this Thursday night program
is called the safe
place because there's so many young
adults young people who are struggling
to find community and we already know
that addiction stem from unmet needs
and a lot of those unmet needs stem from
having lack of Real and True
Community Galatians chapter 6 ver2 tells
us carry each other's burdens and I
praise God for my my small Core group of
brothers and sisters that I talk to on a
regular that when I am stressed when I
need to vent when I need to talk about
and just be loami even the ratchet
version of loami that they see that the
people that I only know that God only
sees right but they have created a safe
place for me to be myself to process my
thoughts to process my feelings to get
feedback and they're sharing with me
their experiences and how they overcame
or what they are stuck with or what they
need to grow in and that Community
allows me to grow even more because now
I can even be more honest with God
through this process of healing so
number one I got to acknowledge the pain
the Lord draw Clos to those who are
brokenhearted but if I'm not a adting
that I'm brokenhearted then God can
never heal the second is finding
Community that's where Healing
Begins Jesus did not battle his he he
batt he struggled with his battles alone
but understand that The Human Side of
him went to his disciples in his dire
need and ask can you just pray for me
can you be there for me but we know that
the that God called his son to
experience this isolation so that way he
can be overcome so that way he can give
us relief in those moments Where We Are
stress and we feel like we don't have
anyone to lean
on Paul tells us that we need to carry
each other's burdens something a dear
sister of mine told me years ago she
said Lo is it
really are are people really your
brothers and sisters and really your
community if you can't be honest and
transparent with them with the things
that you're struggling with and that
dawn on me like man you're right for
years I was going to the church thinking
that these are my community I'm like I
really have no relationship with these
people I have more relationship with my
secular friends because I can be my true
version with them and express what I'm
going to express and say what I got to
say and and how I feel and address the
things without feeling any judgment or
condemnation or having feel or or
feeling like they're about to overp
spiritualize what I'm presenting to them
right if if I go to the church I'm like
hey guys I'm struggling with pornography
they're gonna be like well you got to
cut the internet off you gotta cut all
of these things it's like we let's treat
the symptom let's treat the thing that's
that that you're struggling with in
reality Nah when you pull back the
layers you realize that the reason why
people have addiction to pornography and
to all these other uh U um these
negative behaviors is because there's an
unmet need abandonment issues you know
all of these things that we don't care
to ask to discover because in reality
we've never taken the time to ask those
questions and discover those things for
ourselves third but not least we need to
surrender control
the reason why addiction is such a
powerful tool is because it's the one
thing oh man I'm being I'm being so
honest and blunt with y'all it's the one
thing that I have control over and if I
Surrender the one thing that I have
control over then what do I have to
manage and
control stepping out in faith and really
letting go and letting God guide every
dictate of your life is very scary so we
gravitate to addictions because there is
a fear there because in reality we don't
truly believe that God loves us enough
to give us something better than what we
are addicted to that is a
bar but Romans 8:28 tells us that we
must trust that God can bring beauty
from
ashes can you allow the pain your trauma
allow and being honest through
discovering what's causing this pain the
traumatic events and the unmet needs can
you be honest to God enough to the point
where God then could recreate a new
story in you I'm very honest with my
with with with my struggles I'm very
honest with the journey that I've been
through and I'll never forget I thought
the epitome of my testimony was 10 years
ago where I shared it in front of front
of 10,000 people at a conference and and
more thousands of people watching online
and I thought okay uh uh God has brought
me out of Darkness into this light here
I share my testimony and now this is the
end of the story and since is a part two
to that story because now as a Christian
for 10 years I've realized that I've
learned more about myself in these dark
moments than I did in my moments of
prosperity and my moments of
happiness it was at those moments where
I'm like God this is what I like this is
what I gravitate to this is the pain
that I'm dealing with these are the
unmet needs that I'm not receiving this
is the trauma that I've experienced from
my past relationships from my parents
from my childhood uh uh experiences etc
etc and so Lord this is the reason why
I'm addicted to this and Lord and if you
can't find something better for me to
replace it then I'm not surrendering it
that's how real I had to be with
God and so God has been working through
me through this process to say is this
is this enough for you like
man am I willing to put down this blunt
am I willing to put down the bottle am I
willing to stop scrolling am I willing
to stop over you know overp
spiritualizing thing am I am I willing
to stop overworking to receive the thing
that I desire in my
heart but the reality is we do not
surrender our addictions because we
don't want to lose
control because we at the end of the day
need to be in control of something in
our lives and that is not something that
the gospel speaks
on let's continue let's continue that is
a Christian path to
healing but here's the three steps to
breaking the chains of addiction number
one you have to name the addiction what
is the addiction what is the
vice number two ask what does this
addiction do for me what is a feeling
that it's giving me what is the what
what what is the uh uh the benefits that
I'm receiving from this addiction right
what makes me gravitate to this thing
and then third bring it to the cross for
Redemption God says if we confess our
sins that he is faithful and just but
how are we confessing Lord forgive me
for my sins plural he says okay which
one
well this sin okay why did you commit
that sin well because of the so why did
you respond in that way when this
situation transpired name the
addiction praise God Wendy that it makes
so much sense in your situ praise the
Lord name the addiction that's number
one then ask yourself what does this
addiction do for me it brings me peace
it brings me a moment of of of of you
know it's it's bringing me Comfort it's
allowing me to escape
it's my me time what what does this
addiction do for you and then third
bring that to God like God this is my
addiction I like to overwork I love
overworking because I look at what I've
built look at the what I was able to
provide for my family look how my
business is thriving but God at the end
of the day I'm burnt out I don't spend
time enough with my family I and the
reason why is because I grew up
believing that if you don't work that
you're lazy and those are the lies that
I believed in my entire life and Lord I
know that I don't know how to properly
rest but your word says that I know that
that you can show me how to rest you
said come to me all who are heavy laden
and you will give me rest so God I don't
know how to rest but I'm weary I'm
tired and at the end of the day if I'm
being honest God I feel
alone and so that's why I overwork I try
to escape Lord the reality I don't have
an assurance of
Salvation so I immerse myself in my
family's business
I I try to be a rock for them but in
reality no one's a rock for
me those are the things those are the
things that we need to name to God the
cigarettes all right you named it praise
God what does it do for you for those 15
minutes man I get to clear my mind my my
stress levels are low and but but at the
end of the day what is it doing for you
long
term what what is the thing that God
says I can replace it with something
better and that's what God wants us to
discover with him how how can we really
trust God enough to know that he will
provide something better than the
addiction that we are gravitating to to
escape the reality that we're
facing so how do we
cope and transition to
wholeness understand that coping is a
surviving through temporary fixes that's
what an addiction is I'm overwhelmed I'm
so let me go watch this porn and then I
get my relief but then you have to sit
back now with the guilt and the shame
and the enemy does this and it's an
endless cycle so why am I coping what am
I surviving what am I right so the
second thing is H is at the end of the
day a lot of the addiction stems from
people not living their their their
purpose and their meaning of what
they've been created to
be so I'm just simply surviving
and yo I I shared this
thought I think they posted the video I
think gigg did post it it was a it was
my Sabbath
thought and simply
put that week leading to that Sabbath I
can't tell you how many messages I was
getting about the political climate that
we're in everything that was happening I
mean people are having opinions and
thoughts about everything listen I
didn't know people so knowledgeable
about everything that they knew until
this last month I really didn't I didn't
know people knew about half the things
that that that that's that they were
talking about but you know what I
realized something I'm only
human I'm not God and I can't be upset
the way that you're upset and be
passionate for the same thing that
you're passionate about because I got my
own things I got to deal with and so I
had to go to Nature and I'm listening to
ducks quack I'm seeing the Sun out I'm
see the nice cool I'm feeling the nice
Cool Breeze I'm seeing people walking
dogs I'm seeing people just enjoying
nature and escaping the reality of life
through where God is on the Sabbath and
I don't even know these people religious
or
not and I realize that a lot of people
in the world listen to me carefully
Saints if you're not a Believer if you
are a Believer I need you to listen to
this that the people who are not
Believers of
God are trying to survive the
chaos of the world that they're living
in finances eggs you know the the the
government being dismantled left or
right you know whatever it is right
people are just trying to escape and try
to find a temporary fix for the
craziness that they are experiencing
people are coming to homes and wives are
acting crazy husband are acting crazy
children are acting crazy work all these
demands you know what I'm saying am I
going to get fired not yo these these
are stressful times and people are
trying to
cope but it's
temporary so when God's people are
dealing with the same survival tactics
how are we being a
witness how are we being a witness if
we're coping the same way the world
copes how are we any different when we
are sharing Bible prophecy Allen White
quotes all throughout our Facebook page
debating and arguing with everyone but
that is your way of escaping the reality
that you don't want to address the
trauma the pain or the unmet need I
gotta be right you're wrong I'm right so
I'm going to prove how wrong you are and
I'm gonna quote you to death I'm gonna
comment on anything that I see but what
are you escaping
from because that's just a temporary fix
because at the end of the day you still
got to have to deal with yourself and
you got to have to still deal with
God this is why John chap 10:10 says I
have come that they may have life and
have it to the
full can we say honestly can we say God
I am full of you I am full of your love
I am full of your grace I have peace in
this this chaos and Saints can I tell
you one of the greatest things I've done
is setting boundaries and you'll learn
about setting boundaries where you start
healing when you start going through the
Journey of healing you set boundaries
bro can you not send me no more
political anything bro can you not I'm
good I'm good I even went as far as to
say for every negative thing that you
say about this person I need you to tell
me two positive
things you know God is calling us from
being from
coping for temporary relief to folling
wholeness in Christ
are you whole in Christ can you can you
teach people how you are able to
overcome the addictions of your own life
and how you've been come to the
realization of you being honest and how
you realize that was pain unmet needs
and Trauma that was causing you to get
through the the through these addictions
listen after understanding all this the
drunker the the weed smoker The Gambler
is no different than the person who
immerses himself in religion or over
being an overbearing parent there no
there is no
difference we're just coping with stress
differently and at the end of the day
God wants to get to the heart of the
issue all
right let's continue we're about to wrap
up about to wrap up so here are three
ways of practical ways to heal number
one spend time in scripture and prayer
such a cliche thing that we say as
Christians but in reality I have to come
back the the lives that I've told about
myself or what people have told about me
and combat it with the truths of what
God says about
me and I want to let God speak in the
places that I'm
avoiding so the boldest thing that you
can do is says God this is who I am this
is what I'm addicted to and you know
what I like
it God says thank you so much for your
honesty and your transparency now what
are we going to do moving forward well
God just because I like it doesn't mean
that I want it to remain in my life help
me
God says I will help because you asked
spend time in scripture spend time in
prayer second seek counseling and if you
don't don't believe in going to
therapist then find mentorship or a
community that you can really honestly
talk to that person without feeling
judge and allowing that person to be a
safe place for you even Jesus had his
safe place he had he had it with the
Lazarus Mary and Martha that is where he
was able to be Jesus and not have to
worry about being the Son of God are you
following what I'm saying find white
counsel to guide you and I appreciate my
brothers y'all know who y'all are that
I'm able to talk to on a regular vent my
frustrations they vent their
frustrations whether it be relationships
whether it be marriage whether it be
finances whether it be the political
climate we're in whether it be about
work whatever it is this is sports it
could be whatever ever I got my
community and my counseling I do have my
therapist and we meet once every two
weeks twice a month and I talk to him
just like I talk to I said I I have
Jesus and I have my therapist because
there are some things that I need to
work through I don't have the all the
answers and all the therapist is doing
is giving you the tools for you to
discover and do the work for yourself so
just the same amount of time that you
will spend overworking or spending time
in in finding Bible quotes to prove
people wrong is the same energy that God
says I want to spend to discover who you
really
are seek counseling find a mentor find a
community third create healthy habits
replace the old habits with good habits
exercise Journal engage in intentional
rest not just when you go to sleep at
midnight and you have to wake up six
o'clock in the morning and you got to do
that that process all over again but do
the things that you enjoy
doing listen I've learned how to now
take my time with God and read and study
the things that are important to me in
the season that I'm in I'm not going to
read about Daniel Revelation when I'm
struggling about finances are you
following what I'm saying like I'm going
to read about what God has to say about
finances and I talk to God and I let him
know this is I'm fearful because I've
never made this amount of money before
in my life and if this is the amount
that I need to make in order for me to
live a comfortable life and make an
impact in the community that I'm in and
be an asset to my church then God you
got have to show me oh you're not
listening to
me we sometimes read things to escape
the reality that we living in and it's
like that makes no sense God is like yo
why are you reading about Daniel and the
prophecies and the six seals not saying
that these things are not important
because Bible prophecy we have a short
word and prophecy literally reveals to
us God's plan for our lives and how
history is going to unfold I'm not
negating that so please don't think that
I'm po that that that I'm uh um that um
you know minimizing or downplaying Bible
prophecy my point is are you reading and
studying and praying in the season that
you're in are you looking and
researching on those things that are
currently affecting you that is my point
thank you so much Deborah for saying yes
that mix
Hallelujah but I need you to find
Community mentorship or a counselor I do
need you to do
that because you can't do this on your
own you're not capable of doing it this
is why Jesus says you got to come to
me and this is why I give you principles
in the Bible in Galatians and in James
that you need
Community but third create healthy
habits so what I've done I've been very
intentional in my exercises I I have a
LoveHate relationship with basketball I
try to go play basketball three times a
week I do enjoy playing My Little NBA 2K
from time to time so I decompress I play
my game but I'm listening to a podcast
I'm listening I'm just relaxing I'm
enjoying my time for me CU I can't love
my neighbor if I do not love
myself I can't tell you to relax if I
don't know how to relax I can't tell you
go cast your burdens to God if I don't
know how to cast my burdens to
God do those things journal and and
here's the reason why we need to take
time to journal when we Journal we are
actually expressing our internal
thoughts that we are not able to utterly
share and when you write you'll notice
that there's certain phrases or certain
words that you're constantly repeating
and you're saying okay where is this
coming from and then you're able to take
that journal and talk to God about it
you talk to your community about it you
research about it then it starts
becoming clear as to why you think the
way you think why you gravitate to these
things and now you're having full
discovery of yourself now you can
present yourself to God fully un
alterated and said this is who I really
am and we all know the famous quote
sanctification is a work of a lifetime
sanctification isn't simply just doing
good things is a discovering of
yourself that is the work of a
lifetime we got a few more slides and
we're wrapping
up so here's my encouragement for
Millennials for young adults and youth
and those who are watching that don't
fit into this category here's my
encouragement for you guys number one
it's okay to struggle Jesus meets you in
the struggle not in your
Perfection number two healing is a
journey not a destination it is
literally the work of a lifetime is
discovering who I am in in light of who
God created me to be and his and his
standard and his vision and his goal
that he has for my life and third I'm
not defined by my mistakes because my
identity is in Christ the Bible tells us
that a righteous man falls seven
times why does God call a man who falls
righteous because he keeps getting back
up he's not going to allow life to beat
him down where he doesn't get back up
again he's going to fight through he's
going to discover new things about
himself he's going to be more depressed
and more anxious and saying man God this
is who really I this is who I am I'm I'm
much worse than I ever thought and God
says my grace is sufficient enough for
you I love you my child you've been
created in my image I loved you with an
everlasting love and all of those
promises become real it becomes my own
reality that regardless of what H uh
social media may say and the news May
Say and What politics may be doing I
found peace and I'm rooted in
Jesus Ain nobody can shake
me if if if if society and culture says
I need to make $120,000 to live
comfortably then guess what God you're
gonna have to help me find a way to make
$120,000 actually I need to make 160,000
so I can take that 40,000 and reinvest
it back in my community so I can make a
real impact and live out Isaiah 58 as
you promised me to live and I rest on
that promise come on now that's how we
need to be talking that's how we need to
be living that's how we need to be
thinking and if I struggle praise God
that I'm struggling because a struggle
is an indicator that there's something
living in
Me God meets me at my struggle he does
not meet me at the destination and says
well man you sure was perfect throughout
this journey
nah healing is a journey is not a
destination we're not defined by our
mistake we're not defined by our
addictions we're not defined by any of
those things we are identified by what
Christ says we are
all
right praise the
lord we listen and we don't judge as a
famous Tik Tok trainer was happening
right we listen and we don't judge
number one the church should be a safe
place for
healing the church should be a safe
place for healing this is the community
that you should be finding and meeting
having those unmet needs this is the
community that you should be able to
express yourself tell tell people about
your addictions and not feel judged the
church should be the safe
place number two that first
Thessalonians chapter 5:1 tells us
therefore encourage one another and
build each other up and what I'm seeing
is everybody is tearing each other down
oh you voted for him oh wow you the oh
you this oh I can't even deal with you
we are willing to cut people
off for the most simplest things but the
Bible tells us to encourage one another
to build each other up and I think my
small community of brothers and sisters
who has built me up in those moments
where I cannot build up myself I want to
thank God and I want to thank my
therapist as well to see the things that
he saw in me that I wasn't able to see
in myself at times to encourage me to
build me up for the purpose that I can
then be in encouragement and build other
people up and not tear them down you
still struggling with that well I won't
be opening up to you anymore I won't be
sharing nothing with
you praise the Lord for our dear sister
who was talking uh uh about her
addiction to cigarettes praise the Lord
you named it you pray praise God you
ain't the addictions but God can give
you victory over it but he just has to
acknowledge that you want to surrender
it third but not Le third but not least
right last but not least
let's walk this journey together in love
and
grace how can I have the ability to
judge anyone when I know what I do
behind closed doors how I think how I
act it's the way that you act
act it's the way that you act how can I
judge anybody if I know what I do and
how I think and how I
feel so I realize that all of these are
symptoms from something deeper you tear
people down because that's how you find
your
value you got to prove right because
you've always been told that you've
never been
right the reason why you're alone and
you have no Community is because you
don't know how to be vulnerable and show
love and
grace takor I you're right the majority
of the time the church is not where it
need but we are the church we need to we
have the keys we then create that
Community we create that opportunity for
people this is why we're doing this now
we're doing it live I got I got over 20
people watching and commenting from all
walks of life and all around the the
world tuning in to this you know to hear
me share about addiction holess and
healing and we up here talking to each
other and ain't no judgment coming from
me and ain't no judgment coming from the
people that I'm reading the comments
from
and if we can do it online how much
easier is it to do it in a physical
building I regress last
slide we listen we don't judge those are
the three steps but here's a call to
action here's the three steps and we're
going to conclude number one reflect
what am I escaping from through my
addictions number two once we have
identified what I'm escaping from
through my addictions then I'm GNA
surrender where do I need Christ healing
touch in my life where's the pain point
that I'm not allowing God to enter into
that is where God needs to enter into
and third share how can I support
someone else on this
journey this is why I am I am creating a
community with you because I know the
journey that I had to take to get
here and I want us to join this walk
together the Bible says can two walk
together un less we agree well listen if
you think you have it all together and
you're perfect and I'm a sinner who
makes mistakes We can't agree and we
ain't going to be able to walk this
journey with God together we
can't reflect what am I escaping through
my addictions number two surrender where
do I need Christ healing touch and third
and three how can I support someone else
on this journey that's how you
transition from addiction this is how
the process you find healing and
ultimately Holiness so my prayer is how
many of us tonight know we have some
addictions and some vices that we need
to surrender to God and tonight we're
gonna at least call it out we may not be
able to surrender it but we're going to
say Lord these are my addictions if
that's your desire I ask that you put
one in the chat we can conclude with a
word of prayer and saying God here's my
call to action praise the Lord Sasha
praise the Lord I want to reflect I what
am I escaping from what are the lies
that have been told to be what are my
unmet needs what are my traumas what
what are my child what is the pain point
that I'm not telling anybody uh I'm not
telling anybody about but in reality
it's what's causing me to be the way
that I
am if you're saying Lord I want
surrender Lord I want Power Lord I want
to name this thing and by your grace you
will give me Victory I ask that you may
put one in the chat praise the lord we
got the ones and based on that answer in
reply we can conclude with a word of
prayer let us pray father thank you so
much for this opportunity to be able to
share your word thank you dear Lord for
this new bread um and I thank you so
much for the recept of the the the
comments and the reception of this
message Lord we need to heal Lord we are
not our addictions we are not our
mistakes we're not our shortcomings we
are who you say we are we are children
of the most high created beautifully and
wonderfully in your image and we thank
you for that Lord but we want to call
out those addictions Lord we want to
find healing and more importantly we
want to be whole and Lord your word says
in Matthew 11:28 come all who are weary
and heavy laden and your word promises
us that we will receive rest Lord there
are people who are watching this right
now and listening that have never had
not have have not had a good night's
sleep in years who are dealing with
anxiety who are dealing with pain and
Lord I just ask that you may draw close
to the Brokenhearted as you promis but
allow us to do our part in acknowledging
that we need healing this is my prayer
for I ask this in Jesus precious and
holy name amen and amen so thank you so
much guys for your time we are time is
up but next week Thursday 7 o'clock
we're GNA do another series it's going
to be the charm of Christ the beauty of
Christ we're going to understand the
character of God because as we talk
about these relevant topics about
addiction pornography and there going to
be a lot of topics we're going to be
sharing throughout our our time together
here on Thursday nights it is so vital
and is so important to get to know the
god that we are going to be surrendering
and walking with and so we're going to
be covering that next week um it's
either going to be the prescription or
we're going to do the series entitled
The Beauty of Christ or the charm of
Christ next week Thursday at 7M Central
CH you don't want to miss it please join
our uh mighty Network's Community um
there you will see the video that I
wasn't able to share tonight but also
shoot me an email if you have any
questions if you need prayers um please
shoot me an email uh right there pastor
loami at Living mana. Church and uh I
will get back to you at my earliest
convenience but praise the Lord for all
who's been watching please share this
living bread to those who you know will
be blessed um any young adults who have
missed out these messages or a young
person that you know will be blessed by
this message go ahead and share this
link but until next week Thursday 7 PM
uh may God bless and then may God will
draw close to the pain unmet needs and
the uh victory that we are wanting